Christopher Bowman

Software Engineer - New London, CT | 508-302-9166

cbowman.se@gmail.com | Github | Portfolio | LinkedIn

SUMMARY

Full-stack software engineer with an aptitude for learning new skills quickly, understanding the code I produce and being able to effectively document it for others to read. Strong team player who has contributed to multiple teams and helped drive the design and development of many full-stack applications, and the available statistics are provided in the Work Experience section. Motivated self-starter committed to continuous improvement and learning.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages & Technologies - Python | JavaScript | Java | C++ | SQL | WordPress | Webflow | Figma Libraries & Frameworks - React.js | Next.js | Express.js | Django | Flask Databases - PostgreSQL | MongoDB Cloud Services - Amazon Web Services (AWS)

PROFESSIONAL WORK EXPERIENCE

NextGen - Software Engineer | 8/2023 - Present

- Designed and built the company website with Next.js, React.js and Tailwind CSS with a team of 6 software engineers.
- Helped architect a Node/Express RESTful API using PostgreSQL as the backing data store.
- Created curriculum utilizing Notion and GitHub for collaborative project management. The final curriculum included sections that cover: HTML/CSS, JavaScript, data types, objects, classes, and methods.

Scott's Landscaping, Inc - Senior Software Engineer | 2/2023 - Present

(https://scottslandscaping.org) (https://github.com/cbowman422/scottslandscaping)

- Designed and built a responsive web application with React.js to replace the company's old and dated website.
- Improved overall accessibility (A11y) across devices and increased user retention rate by 15%.
- Enhanced user experience and user interface (UX/UI), resulting in a 30% increase in website engagement and a 20% decrease in bounce rate.
- Managed the transfer of the domain registrar, email hosting, and updated DNS records to Namecheap and Vercel resulting in a 60% decrease in annual hosting cost. Worked closely with the team at Scott's Landscaping to ensure that downtime was kept to a minimum and ensure changes did not impact day-to-day business.
- Managed email complications by executing a transfer from POP to IMAP resulting in a 100% decrease of lost emails.

SpaceLab - DevOps Engineer Internship | 6/2023 - 8/2023 (https://spacelab.space/)

- Built scalable backend environment utilizing cloud-native functionalities (AWS EC2, AWS Fargate, etc.)
- Led the charge to design the cloud-native deployment system using AWS Fargate and Docker to achieve scalability
 while also balancing cost.
- Leveraged ChatGPT to help supplement my skills and improve my knowledge on topics such as AWS, GraphQL, and Docker.

General Dynamics Electric Boat - Engineer II | 8/2020 - 11/2022

- Produced FEA models for 2 Virginia and 1 Columbia class Submarine, using ABAQUS scripting and Python.
- Analyzed technical models with Finite Element Method software ABAQUS/CAE and in-house code.
- Collaborated with engineers to produce well-organized and professional documentation for calculations.

University of Massachusetts, Amherst - Teaching Assistant | 1/2019 - 12/2019

- Provided support and mentored two separate engineering classes while gaining important leadership experience.
- Hosted 2 and 3-hour, well-attended, office hour sessions twice weekly for 14 weeks and accurately graded over 300
 projects of high technical difficulty.

EDUCATION

University of Massachusetts, Amherst - Bachelor of Science in Mechanical Engineering | 5/2020

- 3.44 GPA
- Relevant coursework includes: Pre-Calc, Calculus 1 & 2, Multivariable Calculus, Differential Equations, Statics, Dynamics, Engineering Statistics, Linear Algebra, Intro to Computer Science and Intro to Electrical Engineering.

General Assembly - Software Engineering Immersive | 2/2023

- Focused on product development fundamentals, object-oriented programming, MVC frameworks, data modeling, and team collaboration strategies.
- Mentored students during group work and provided support with debugging code.

SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT PROJECTS

Money Mania - 3/2023

(https://github.com/cbowman422/Money-Mania-Frontend)

Tech Stack: MongoDB | Express | React.js | Node.js | HTML | CSS

- Developed a MERN application geared towards student finance education, which placed 1st place in the GA 2023 Gamifying Hackathon.
- Led a team of 3 UX/UI designers and 4 software engineers to accomplish MVP in a 4-day sprint.
- Designed the software architecture to fit the requisites of the React framework.
- Responsible for the Node.js, Express, and MongoDB RESTful back-end server and rebuilding 3 React.js front-end pages.

Messenger - 2/2023

(https://github.com/cbowman422/messenger)

Tech Stack: Socket.IO | MongoDB | Express | React.js | Node.js | HTML | CSS

- Acted as project lead for a dynamic messaging MERN application employing Socket.IO for real-time chat room messaging.
- Responsible for integrating a new library, Socket.IO, into a MERN application with authorization in order to accomplish MVP in a 1-week sprint.

HAPI HOUR - 12/2022

(https://github.com/cbowman422/hapi-hour)

Tech Stack: React.js | JavaScript | HTML | CSS | Grid | Flexbox | thecocktaildb.com

- HAPI Hour is a front-end web application built with React.js to navigate objects from a 3rd party API (thecocktaildb.com).
- Coordinated with another software engineer to accomplish MVP in a 1-week sprint and was mainly responsible for developing the React components.